Celdrick N. **KUTA**Data Scientist | Data Analyst

♀ Lawrenceville, GA

makedatashine.com



Data science professional with 5+ years of experience across range of technical and non-technical roles. Dedication in data collection, cleaning and organizing data for use by technical and non-technical personnel. Significant Industry experience with developing answers through incorporating state-of-the-art machine learning and deep learning techniques to perform predictive modeling, quantitative as well as detailed data analysis helping organizations find new clients, expand their businesses and make informed decisions.

EDUCATION

May 2021	Master o	f Science	in	Applied	Statistics	Illinois S	State	Univers	ity, Normal USA	٩.
		_								

Jul 2016 Master of Science in Computer Science University of Yaoundé, Cameroon.

Jul 2010 Bachelor of Science in Mathematics and Computer Science from University of Buea, Cameroon.

SKILLS

Programming Python, R, SQL, MATLAB, Java, C, C++, Scala, Linux, ŁTŁX, HTML5, Javascript, CSS Frameworks Hadoop, Spark, PySpark, AWS, Python (eg. scikit-learn, numpy, pandas, matplotlib)

Databases IBM DB2, Oracle Database, Microsoft SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL

Tools Jupyter Notebook, Eclipse, Visual Studio Code, AWS SageMaker, git, Spyder, BigQuery

Modeling Regression, Classification (Logistic, Decision Trees, Random Forest), Clustering(hierarchical, Recommendation Systems and K-means), Naïve Bayes, PCA, SVM, Boosting and Bagging,

Time Series Analysis

Operating systems Mac OS, Windows Server, Windows 11, Linux Redhat, Linux Centos

Others A/B testing, ETL, Data science pipeline (cleaning, wrangling, visualization, modeling, interpre-

tation), Statistics, Time Series, Experimental design, Hypothesis testing, OOP, OOD, APIs, Excel,

Cross-Functional Collaboration.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Present -Jun 2021

Data Scientist, ELEVATED TECHNOLOGIES, Houston-TX

- > Part of the Data Science team at Elevated technologies that was tasked with the design and validation of an insurance product to be able to predict the severity of insurance claims post an unforeseen event for their client.
- > Utilized Python to implement supervised machine learning and accommodated all the past transactions' history and the point of contact information to create enhance features to predict insurance claim severity on 60MB of structured data.
- > Reduced total process time by 20% and increase accuracy of existing model by more than 10% than previous years.
- > Client is able to plan promotions accordingly by understanding important factors for claims severity.

 Python Glue ETL AWS SQL Athena

May 2021 -Feb 2020

Data Scientist, Ортімим, Houston-TX

- > Tasked with automating the process of detecting and localizing defects in real time found in steel manufacturing for their client.
- > Designed and Implemented a state-of-the-art Deep Learning architecture in python on historical imagery data with 4 types of defects to classify image as defect or defect free, applying segmentation model to localize defects when present.
- > New market strategy for streamlining sales cycles from 2 months to 1 month raising sales team performance Month over Month (MoM) by 40%
- > The Client is now able to scale up quality production with minimal budget while minimizing pollution through waste emission.

Python Windows Server Deep Learning

Jan 2020 -Mar 2019

Associate Data Scientist, HIREWELL, Chicago-IL

- > Leveraged classification machine learning techniques on extensive amount of unstructured data pertaining to client's customers verified reviews to determine if they are satisfied with the product or not.
- > Web scraped data with python beautiful Soup for various meal kit variations for food delivery company from multiple sources.
- > Recommended existing delivery method with findings from consumer data analysis reports to further consumer awareness, led to 50% increase in new clientele.

Python Linux server Jupyter notebook

Jun 2018 -Nov 2016

Data Analyst, PANUS SOFTWARE, Buea-Cameroon

- > Coordinated detailed industry analysis, research, drafted reports and developed analytical insights for Banking Clients to optimize marketing strategy by performing customer segmentation in R.
- > Designed 5+ dashboards for clients leveraging over 20+ user requested features ranging from Sales, Revenue, Profits, Returns & discounts etc.
- > Spearheading business development expanding dashboard sales to nearby markets raising revenue by 250%.

R Tableau Power BI

ANGUAGES





- > Passionate
- > Motivated
- > Autonomous

PROJECTS

NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING

☑ makedatashine.com

Topic modelling with Kmeans clustering manchine learning in order to group customer reviews based on recurring patterns.

Python SQL

RETAIL PRICE OPTIMIZATION

makedatashine.com

Use price elasticity to set optimal price to maximize profit while leveraging customers responsiveness.

Python Excel

SALES FORECASTING

☑ makedatashine.com

Implement Facebook prophet for time series sales data to forecast future sales taking into account seasonality, trends, anomaly

Python Flask

RECOMMENDATION SYSTEM

makedatashine.com

Leveraged machine learning to build and deploy a Recommender System in Python based on collaborative filtering on over 2MB data of verified customer reviews and ratings

Python AWS SageMaker Heroku



66 References

Hubert Foy

Director, AFRICSIS

 hfoy@africsis.org +233 554 603 605

Amin Bahmanian

Supervisor, ISU

@ mbahman@ilstu.edu +1(309) 438-7707